Guide to the American Left Ephemera Collection, 1875-2015 AIS.2007.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Socialist Party USA (SPUSA), XVII.
  - "Rational Prohibition", An Address to Temperance Workers, Delivered in Los Angeles, June 22, 1902, By Walter L. Young (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - "What's So and What Isn't", By John M. Work, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - "The Cold War and the Russian Bogeyman: A Socialist Analysis" (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - "Why I am a Socialist", By Norman Thomas (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - "Democracy and Revolution", By Friedrich Adler (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - A Socialist Party of America Membership Card (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - "Capitalism, Socialism, Communism?- A Debate" (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - "Convict 9653, America's Vision Maker", Story of Eugene Victor Debs, the United States' Great Socialist Anti-Militarist, By Guy A. Aldred (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Certain Misconceptions, A Few Current Objections to Socialism Answered, by John M. Work, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - Are There Classes in America?, by Ralph Korkngold (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Little Blue Book, No. 1703, Organizing the World for Socialism, Clarence Senior, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - ASQ, American Socialist Quarterly Reprints, No. 1, "Towards Socialist Reorientation", By Haim Kantorovitch (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - "Problems of Revolutionary Socialism", By Haim Kantorovitch (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - The Essence of Socialism, by William H. Watts, 1910 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - "Wage-Labor and Capital", By Karl Marx (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - The Socialist Appeal, August-September, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Socialist Party Leaflet, No. 4, "How Socialists Organized the Unions in Germany", By Robert Hunter (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Socialism, What it is, and How to Get it, by Oscar Ameringer, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - "Scientific Principles of History, Political Economy and Sociology Wrapped in One Bundle (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - National Constitution of the Socialist Party (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - The Socialist Party of Ohio Poll Inspector Certificates (2), 1912 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - "Socialist Party Platform" (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - "National Constitution of the Socialist Party", 1912 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - "A Political Guide for the Workers", Socialist Party Campaign Book, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - "An Open Letter to Progressives", By Norman Thomas, 1928 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - "For Socialist America", National Platform, Socialist Party, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - "The ABC of Socialism", By Fred Henderson (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Technocracy and Socialism, by Paul Blanshard, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - A Worker's World, by David P. Berenberg, 1931 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - "A Plan for America", Official Campaign Handbook of the Socialist Party, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - "Inflation, Who Wins and Who Loses?", By Maynard C. Krueger, March 23, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - "The Case for Socialism", By Fred Henderson (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - "Democracy and Revolution", By Friedrich Adler (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - "Socialist Handbook", 1937 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - Numerous Issues of Labor and Socialist Press Service, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - "Constitution of the Socialist Party", 1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Young Socialist, An Amateur Monthly Socialist Magazine (2), March and April, 1902 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Platform and Program of the Socialist Party of Turtle Creek Borough. General Election", November 8, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - The International Socialist Review, April, 1910 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Flyer to Attend The Socialist Party's Monthly Meetings (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Essentials of Socialism, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Twenty Years of Social Pioneering, 1926 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - A Coverless League for Industrial Democracy Booklet (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Now It Must Be Done, by Irwin St. John Tucker, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "To-Day's Problems and Their Solutions", By 150 Able Writers (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - "The Land of the Free Socialist America" (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - "The New Capitalism and the Socialist", By Harry W. Laidler, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "Socialist Songs With Music", Compiled By Charles H. Kerr, 1906 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "The New Deal, A Socialist Analysis", By Norman Thomas, December 15, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Membership Card for the Socialist Party of the State of Ohio (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Socialist Party Cards (3) (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - "Soldiers, Sailors and Socialism" (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Ohio Socialist Bulletin, May 1911 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - The Emporia Convincer Newspaper, May 18, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Land and Labor Newspaper, March 7, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - The Findlay Call, July 1 1911 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - The American Guardian - Vol. 14 No. 35-Vol. 22 No. 41, May 12, 1933-July 14, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 22-86)
  - Issues of The Pioneer, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 52)
  - A Letter from the Socialist Party National Campaign Committee in Regard to its Negro Work Sub-Committee, September 12, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 53)
  - The Comrade: An Illustrated Socialist Monthly (4), July, November and December, 1902, and February, 1903 (Box 14, Folder 54)
  - Issues of The Journal of the Socialist Party of Illinois (7), 1984-1986 (Box 14, Folder 55)
  - Appeal to Reason Promotional Letter (Box 14, Folder 56)
  - Criminology, Crimes and Criminals (Box 14, Folder 57)
  - Wayland's Monthly, May, 1905 (Box 14, Folder 58)
  - Shop Talks on Economics (Box 14, Folder 59)
  - Reception and Dance Given in Honor of the Delegates to the State Convention, March 20, 1909 (Box 14, Folder 60)
  - Price List, ca. 1910 (Box 14, Folder 61)
  - Your Unions Your Future, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 62)
  - A.B.C. of Socialism, 1924 (Box 14, Folder 63)
  - "The Young People's Socialist League" Flyer, ca. 1971 (Box 14, Folder 64)
  - "Studies in Socialism: What is Yours and How to Get it" H.L. Riggs, October 1910 (Box 14, Folder 65)
  - To-Night Captain C.C. Ross Flyer, 1912 (Box 14, Folder 66)
  - "Packingtown" Pamphlet, 1907 (Box 14, Folder 67)
  - "The Roman Catholic Church Answered: Attack of Roman Catholic Church on Socialism" Pamphlet, 1911 (Box 14, Folder 68)
  - "Studies in Socialism" Pamphlet, 1906-1907 (Box 14, Folder 69)
  - "Monkeys and Monkeyettes: A Reply to ex-President Roosevelt" W.F. Ries, 1909 (Box 14, Folder 70)
  - Newsletter to Members of SLP and SDP (Box 14, Folder 71)
  - Pearson's Magazine, December 1918 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - "Life and Deeds of Uncle Sam" Oscar Ameringer pamphlet, 1912 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - "The Worker in American History" James O'Neal, Socialist Party Library Reading PA, 1921 (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - "What Shall We Do for Food?" Flyer, 1910 (Box 26, Folder 30)
  - 1956 National Platform of the Socialist Party of the United States (Box 26, Folder 31)
  - Beware the Menace of Socialism, 1911 (Box 26, Folder 32)
  - The Socialist Party. Leaflet, 1908 (Box 26, Folder 33)
  - District of Columbia Socialist Party Local, March/April 1911 (Box 26, Folder 34)
  - Mayer Hoan Answers Critics pamphlet, 1933 (Box 26, Folder 35)
  - "Fight the Jingoes today or in the Trenches Tomorrow", November 1915 (Box 26, Folder 36)
  - "Bebel's Reminiscences" Translated by Ernest Untermann, 1911 (Box 26, Folder 37)
  - "The Head-Fixing Industry" John Keracher pamphlet, 1955 (Box 26, Folder 38)
  - "Socialism: Utopian and Scientific" Charkles Kerr, 1913 (Box 26, Folder 39)
  - "The Passing of Capitalism" Isador Ladoff, October 1901 (Box 26, Folder 40)
  - "In and Out of the Yoke" Charles Edward Russell, 1916 (Box 26, Folder 41)
  - "Railroading in the United States: also the James Boys; also As to Law and Order" Ben Hanford, December 1901 (Box 26, Folder 42)
  - "Is Competition the Life of Trade" Joseph Wanhope, 1908 (Box 26, Folder 43)
  - "No!: Steps to Create Peace", 1987 (Box 26, Folder 44)
  - The American Circus, Leaflet, 1902 (Box 26, Folder 45)
  - Mouseland: Cartoon Flyer, ca. 1980s (Box 26, Folder 46)
  - A Socialist Program for New York, 1946 (Box 26, Folder 47)
  - The New Appeal Almanac for 1918 (Box 26, Folder 48)
  - Red Falcons of America Manual, ca. 1930s (Box 26, Folder 49)
  - Minnesota Socialist Party Ballot, 1911 (Box 26, Folder 50)
  - "Europe in Revolution" Scott Nearing Rand School Pamphlet, 1920 (Box 26, Folder 51)
  - "The Fighting Editor OR Warren and the Appeal to Reason" George D. Brewer, 1910 (Box 26, Folder 52)
  - "The Trinity of Plunder" August Claessens, 1916 (Box 26, Folder 53)
  - "The Fighting for Freedom" George H. Shoat, ca. 1950s (Box 26, Folder 54)
  - "Poems for the People" W.F. Phelps, 1898 (Box 26, Folder 55)
  - Socialist Party Anti-War Flyers. 1 Ad, 3 Flyers, 1914-1916 (Box 26, Folder 56)
  - Free Catalogue of Little Blue Books, 1920 (Box 26, Folder 57)
  - "A Paradox Explained" George A. Eastman (Box 26, Folder 58)
  - Municipal Campaign Book Social-Democratic Party, 1912 (Box 26, Folder 59)
  - "The World's Revolutions" Ernest Untermann, 1906 (Box 26, Folder 60)
  - "Brau-Industrie und Braubeiter Bewegung in Amerika" Hermann Shulter, 1910 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - "Albany: Crisis in Government" Louis Waldman, 1920 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - "American Pauperism and the Abolition of Poverty" Isador Ladoff. Socialist Party Library, Reading PA, 1907 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - "Ethics and the Materialist Conception of History" Karl Kautsky. Socialist Party Library, Reading PA, 1907 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - "The Rebel at Large" May Beals, 1906 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - "What's So and What Isn't" John M. Work. Socialist Party Library, Reading PA, 1909 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - "The Changing Order" Oscar Lovell Triggs. Socialist Party Library, Reading PA, 1908 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - "The American Farmer" A.M. Simmons, 1902 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - "Puritanism" Clarence Meily. Socialist Party Library, Reading PA, 1911 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - "A Benevolent Feudalism" W.J. Ghent, 1902 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - "The Physical Basis of Mind and Morals" M.H. Fitch. Socialist Party Library, Reading PA, 1908 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - "The Red Book for Education and Organization" Ira C. Tilton, 1912 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - "The American Socialists and the War" Edited by Alexander Trachtenberg and Morris Hillquit, 1917 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - "Communism and Christianism" Bishop William Montgomery, 1920 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - "Marxism and Darwinism" Anton Pannekock, 1912 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - "The Making of the World" Dr. Wilhelm Meyer, 1906 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Political Action. 68 Issues, Bound, July 1911- November 1912 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - CC Edwards for Assembly, Campaign Poster, 1912 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Muscatine County Socialist vo. 5 no. 250, November 1917 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - The Leader vol. III no.1, 1914 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - The National Rip-Saw vol. VII no. 9, November 1910 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - The New Voice Vol. I no. 2, June 1919 (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - The Pioneer Vol. VIII no. 15, October 1937 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - The American Freeman, No. 1891, February 1932 (Box 34, Folder 14a)
  - The American Freeman, No. 1940, May 1934 (Box 34, Folder 14b)
  - Socialist Worker's Party (SWP), XVIII.
    In 1928 the CPUSA expelled American Communists sympathetic to Leon Trotsky and his faction battling Joseph Stalin for control of the international Communist movement. They reconstituted themselves as the Communist League of America. Although a tiny group, estimated at perhaps 100 members, it included several prominent founders of American Communism (e.g. James Cannon) and some talented and energetic organizers. The group made contact with Trotsky sympathizers in other countries, established a journal, The Militant, and pursued an energetic propaganda campaign that led to modest expansion.
    In 1934, the group entered the Socialist Party en masse, establishing a caucus within the SP. This strategy facilitated recruitment to the Trotskyist group but inevitably aggravated factionalism within the Socialist Party. In the summer of 1937, the SP began expelling Trotskyists. Those remaining left the SP and established the Socialist Workers Party in December 1937. While still a small group, they had expanded to more than 1000 members between 1928 and 1937, included a number of prominent intellectuals, and had somewhat more political prominence than might be expected from their numbers.
    However the movement's growth was repeatedly compromised by factional splits in which ideological disputes among the leadership promoted splits and formation of tiny rival organizations. In the most serious of these episodes, perhaps 40% of the SWP's membership seceded to found the Worker's Party lead by Max Shachtman.
    By the 1960s, although the SWP still had not grown much larger than its peak membership before the Shachtmanite split it looked somewhat more significant. The collapse of the CPUSA after 1956 left the SWP as the most energetic and visible of the Old Left parties. Their endorsement of Malcolm X garnered some sympathy among Black radicals, and their support for the Cuban Revolution, such as their participation in the Fair Play for Cuba Committee, also earned support among the emerging New Left generation. They likewise played a prominent role in the anti-Vietnam War movement helping to organize some of the largest demonstrations in Washington, D.C. and other major cities.
    In the long run, however, none of this activity resulted in permanent expansion of the organization beyond the modest levels that had characterized it throughout its history.
    - "Vote for Socialism in 1956" Pamphlet (Box 11, Folder 87)
    - "Let the People Vote on War!" Pamphlet, ca. 1938 (Box 11, Folder 88)
    - "A Public Forum for the Discussion of the Socialist Workers Party Program" Leaflet, October 15 1960 (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - "The Voice of Socialism: Radio Speeches by the Socialist Workers Party Candidates in the 1948 Election" Pamphlet, August 1948 (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - "Manifesto of the Fourth International on The Imperialist War and the Proletarian Revolution" Pamphlet, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - How to Fight War, By James Burnham, March, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - Union-Smashing in Sacramento, The Truth About the Criminal Syndicalism Trial, By Herbert Solow, August, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - The Stalinists on the Waterfront, By Art Preis, April, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - "What Makes Latin America Explosive" Flyer (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - "A Worker for President, Vote Socialist Workers" Flyer (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - Desegregation! Labor's Stake in the Fight for Negro Equality, By Jean Simon, October, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - The United States and the Second World War, The European Revolution and Tasks of The Revolutionary Party, Resolutions of Eleventh Convention of the American Trotskyist Movement, March 1945 (Box 11, Folder 98)
    - "The Truth About Jerry Brown" Pamphlet (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - War and the 4th International, July, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - Stop McCarthyism!, April 1954 (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - "Build a Labor Party Now", By George Clarke, August, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - "Fight the Slave Labor Law!", July, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - Four Pamphlets from The Case for Socialism as Presented at the Famous Minneapolis Labor Trial Collection. Pamphlets Entitled "Socialism on Trial", "Why We are in Prison", "In Defense of Socialism" and "Who are the 18 Prisoners", March, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 104)
    - The Case of the Legless Veteran, By James Kutcher (Box 11, Folder 105)
    - The Coming American Revolution, By James P. Cannon, April, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 106)
    - The People's Front, The New Betrayal, by James Burnham, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 107)
    - "Vote Socialist, Steve Bresler for A.S. President, Young Socialist Alliance" Flyer (Box 11, Folder 108)
    - Why We Defend the Soviet Union, by Albert Goldman (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - "For a Workers & Farmers Government Vote for Dobb for President, Carlson for Vice-President" Pamphlet (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - "For a Real Alternative Vote Socialist, Dobbs for President, Weiss for Vice-President, Students for Dobbs and Weiss" Sticker (Box 11, Folder 111)
    - American Workers Need a Labor Party, By Joseph Hansen, November, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - Flyer Advertising a "United Protest Memorial Meeting for Three Wayne State University Students" (Box 11, Folder 113)
    - Discussion Bulletin No. 1, "The Kremlin's Satellite States in Eastern Europe, Yugoslavia, Marxist Theory, and our Perspectives", By E.R. Frank, April, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - Discussion Bulletin No. 3, "The Class Nature of the Buffer Countries in Eastern Europe", By M. Stein, June, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 115)
    - "Wherever death may surprise us, let it be welcome if our battle cry has reached even one receptive ear and another hand reaches out to take up our arms..." -Che (Box 11, Folder 116)
    - Ten Years: History and Principles of the Left Opposition, November 1933 (Box 11, Folder 117)
    - "A Fighting Program For Labor: Jobs for All" Pamphlet, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 118)
    - "Viva la Huelga! The Struggle of the Farmworkers" Jose G. Perez, 1973 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Worker's Democracy no. 34, May/June 1990 (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - "Be His Payment High or Low: The American Working Class of the Sixties" Martin Glaberman, 1969 (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Socialist Review no. 60, November/December 1981 (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Campaign Pamphlet, Why Working People..., 1980 (Box 39, Folder 20)
    - Other Trotskyists
      Despite its small numbers—a peak combined membership of no more than 3,000 in all of its tendencies--the American Trotskyist movement suffered from factionalism and splits throughout its history. That was probably a function of the movement's ideological heritage and structure. While Socialist and Social Democratic Parties in the US and elsewhere also experienced factional conflict, except in the years immediately following the Bolshevik Revolution, these did not generally produce organizational splits because the parties conceived of themselves as big tent electoral coalition parties, not unlike their bourgeois counterparts. The Trotskyists, in contrast, took from their Communist heritage Leninist notions of centralized and ideologically coherent parties that enforced correct line discipline on all members. But while the Communists had an institutional apparatus—the Comintern and its successors—to establish the terms and limits of orthodoxy, the Trotskyists had no such institutional counterpart. People who believed that establishing and adhering to a correct line was the sine qua non of worthwhile political activity thus had no alternative to splits when they decided that their parent organization had erred grievously in its ideological and strategic judgments.
      The largest and most enduring American Trotskyist organization was the Socialist Workers Party (SWP). Other Trotskyist groups represented in the American Left Ephemera Collection include the Workers Party (followers of Max Shachtman), the Spartacist League (an offshoot of the Shachtmanites), and the Workers World Party (followers of ex-CP and ex-SWP member Sam Marcy).
      - The New International, A Symposium on The New Europe, July, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 119)
      - "The Communist Party at the Crossroads: Toward Democratic Socialism or Back to Stalinism", By H.W. Benson (Box 11, Folder 120)
      - "No More Three Mile Islands! Jobs For All! Fight the Bosses and Their Government", March 28, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 121)
      - 3 Worker's World Party Pamphlets Stating "People's Needs, Yes! Profits and War, No!" (Box 11, Folder 122)
      - Next- A Labor Party!, By Jack Ranger, December, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 123)
      - What is Revolutionary Leadership? (Box 11, Folder 124)
      - The Fight to Implement Busing for Labor/Black Defense to Stop Racist Attacks and to Smash Fascist Threats, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 125)
      - Fourth International, The American Empire, August, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 126)
      - The New International, A Monthly Organ of Revolutionary Marxism, December, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 72)
      - The New International, A Monthly Organ of Revolutionary Marxism, October, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 73)
      - Dobbs-Weiss Campaign Flyer, 1960 (Box 39, Folder 19)
  - The American Freeman, No. 1941, June 1934 (Box 39, Folder 14c)
  - The Ohio Socialist no. 72, June 1919 (Box 39, Folder 15)
  - "Jobs, Peace, Freedom. Vote Socialist", 1980 (Box 39, Folder 16)
  - "Pyramid of the Capitalist System" Socialist Poster, 1911 (Box 35, Folder 18)
  - Science and Revolution by Ernest Untermann, 1905 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - The Passing of Capitalism by Isador Ladoff, 1901 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Austin Lewis, Rise of the American Proletariat, 1907 (Box 39, Folder 18)
- Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), XIX.
  SDS began as the student affiliate of the League for Industrial Democracy (LID), an organization of Fabian minded Socialist intellectuals and labor union officials that published detailed policy statements on public issues from a Social Democratic point of view. The LID sponsored a Student League for Industrial Democracy (SLID) that had substantial membership at several colleges and universities in the Debs era, but by the late 1950s both the parent organization and the student wing had declined to tiny remnants. However, the student wing had picked up energetic organizers influenced by the emerging New Left. In 1960 they rename the organization Students for a Democratic Society, suggesting how they had been influenced by such New Left oriented thinkers as C. Wright Mills. Mills criticized what he called the "labor metaphysic" of the Old Left and urged young activists to pursue new ideas and new strategies. This began a process of estrangement from the parent organization over such issues as anti-communism and the Vietnam War. The ILD was militantly anti-Communist and supported U.S. policy in Vietnam. Most SDS members had scorn for Communism (at least of the capital "C" variety; some of them could reasonably be called small "c" communists), but they were anti-anti-Communist because they considered American anti-Communism as a paranoid crusade stifling creative thinking in the United States. SDS vigorously opposed U.S. policy in Vietnam. SDS did not formally break with the LID until 1965, but the mutual antagonism between the LID and SDS was quite evident several years before.
  In its early years SDS was a tiny organization with only a few hundred members on a couple of dozen campuses. It was far smaller than the Student Peace Union, and indeed smaller than the youth organizations of Old Left parties like the CP and the SWP. But the organization began to attract attention after the publication of its Port Huron Statement in 1962 in which it criticized both sides in the Cold War, discussed how both failed to satisfy unfulfilled utopian longings, and advocated as its alternative what it called participatory democracy. SDS also attracted new members through its early collaboration with the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and its early opposition against the War in Vietnam. It expanded rapidly after its sponsorship of the first large demonstration against the War in Vietnam in April 1965.